Guide to the Zdenek Nemeck Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1925-71; Series II; 6.25; (20 boxes)
  - NOVELS
    - "Na západ od Panonie"
      - Royalties and fees, 1946, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - "New York: zamlzeno"
      - Correspondence with publishers, contracts and royalties, 1931-34, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
      - Publicity, 1931-32 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      - Rejection notices, 1930, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - Reviews, 1932-34 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - "Tvrdá zeme": Chapters I - VII, typescripts
      - First draft, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 96-104)
      - Second draft (Box 4, Folder 105-11)
      - Third draft, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112-20)
      - Fourth draft, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 121-28)
      - Correspondence about translations, 1954-56 (Box 4, Folder 129)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 130)
      - Publicity, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 131)
      - Research material, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
      - Reviews, 1954, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 133)
      - English translation: Chapters I - IX, typescripts, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134-42)
  - DRAMA
    - One Act
      - "Balada o Kátince"
        See also: Box 1, folders 16, 18
        - Contracts and correspondence, 1939, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 143)
        - Photographs, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 144)
        - Programs, 1940, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 145)
        - Publicity, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 146)
        - Reviews, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 147)
        - Royalties, 1941, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 148)
      - "Bílá barva"
        - [Bílá barva]: holograph entitled "Král - clovek," bound with an unidentified play, [1940?] (Box 6, Folder 149)
        - Contracts, correspondence, and research notes, [1940]-41 (Box 6, Folder 150)
      - "Ceho se lidé bojí"
        See: "V horách jsou záveje", Box 6, folder 166
      - "Den nejjasnejsí": holograph signed, dated and typescript, corrected, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 151)
      - "Inserát": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 152)
      - "Král - clovek"
        See: "Bílá barva", Box 6, folder 149
      - "Lichy pocet": typescript, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 153)
      - "The Lodger": English translation of "Podnájemník": typescript and fragment, [1951?] (Box 6, Folder 154)
      - "Podnájemník"
        - Drafts: early and later, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 155)
        - Programs, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 156)
      - "Pojistka": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - "Poslední sázka"
        - Publicity, [1958] (Box 6, Folder 158)
      - "Poslední vule"
        - Playbills, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 159)
      - "Príjezd": mimeographs, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 160)
      - "Der schmale Pfad": German translation of "Uzká cesta": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 161)
      - "Der schmale Pfad: Film - Synopsis": German translation of "Uzká cesta": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 162)
      - "A Strange Insurance - Policy": English translation of "Pojistka": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 163)
      - "Tri aktovky: [Lekárnické vázky. Pokusení v demokracii. Bílá barva]": Contract, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 164)
      - "Uzká cesta": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 165)
      - "V horách jsou záveje": holograph and typescript, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - More than one act
      - "Dolores"
        - Early draft: typescript, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 167)
        - Later draft: typescript, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 168)
      - "Hvad koster et menneskelív?": Danish translation of "Zac lidsky zivot": typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 169)
      - "The Light Year": English translation of "Svetelny rok": typescripts, copy 1 & 2, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 170-71)
      - "Most"
        - Contracts, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 172)
        - Correspondence about English translation, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 173)
        - Correspondence with publishers and producers, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 174)
        - Programs and posters, [1938] (Box 7, Folder 175)
        - Reviews, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 176)
        - Royalties, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 177)
      - "Penezokaz"
        - Typescript, corrected, [early 1940's] (Box 7, Folder 178)
        - Correspondence with publishers and producers, 1945-46 (Box 7, Folder 179)
        - Programs, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 180)
        - Royalties, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 181)
        - Reviews, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 182)
      - "Primus Tropicus"
        - Contracts and royalties, 1925-47 (Box 7, Folder 183)
        - Playbills, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 184)
        - Reviews and caricature, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 185)
      - "Rukopis casu"
        - Contracts, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 186)
        - Correspondence with publishers and producers, 1945-47 (Box 7, Folder 187)
        - Programs and playbills, 1946, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 188)
        - Reviews, 1946-47 (Box 7, Folder 189)
        - Royalties, 1946-47 (Box 7, Folder 190)
      - "Smysl diplomacie"
        See: "Primus Tropicus", Box 7, folder 183
      - "Svetelny rok"
        See: "Dolores", Box 6, folder 167
      - "Zac lidsky zivot?"
        See also: Box 6, folder 169
      - "Zac lidsky zivot?"
        - Awards, 1937, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 191)
        - Contracts, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 192)
        - Correspondence, 1935-36 (Box 7, Folder 193)
        - Correspondence about the production in French, 1936-37 (Box 7, Folder 194)
        - Photographs, 1936, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 195)
        - Programs, playbills, posters, 1946-47 (Box 7, Folder 196)
        - Publicity, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 197)
        - Reviews, 1936-48 (Box 7, Folder 198)
        - Royalties, 1936-43 (Box 7, Folder 199)
      - "Zivot císlo dve"
        - First draft: mimeograph, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 200)
        - Second draft: mimeograph, corrected (Box 7, Folder 201)
        - Third draft: mimeograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 202)
        - Playbills, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 203)
        - Reviews, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 204)
      - Unidentified play
        See: [Bílá barva], Box 6, folder 149
  - TRAVEL BOOKS
    - "Dopisy ze Senegambie"
      - Contracts, 1937-42 (Box 8, Folder 205)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1937-42 (Box 8, Folder 206)
      - Reviews, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 207)
    - "Islandské dopisy"
      - "Uvod," and all the letters - typescripts, [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 208)
      - Dopis 1: "Tonicce", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 209)
      - Dopis 2: "Básníku z atelieru v Lucerne", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 210)
      - Dopis 3: "Josefovi, ktery rád cestuje", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 211)
      - Dopis 4: "Otakarovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 212)
      - Dopis 5: "Jaromírovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 213)
      - Dopis 6: "Príteli z Klementina", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 214)
      - Dopis 7: "Janu ze Semil", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 215)
      - Dopis 8: "Poldicce", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 216)
      - Dopis 9: "Vojtovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 217)
      - Dopis 10: "Arnostovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 218)
      - Dopis 11: "Oldrichovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 219)
      - Dopis 12: "Príteli ze ctvrté sekce", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 220)
      - Dopis 13: "Josefu sousedovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 221)
      - Dopis 14: "Panu uciteli od rybníka", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 222)
      - Dopis 15: "Oldovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 223)
      - Dopis 16: "Surikovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 224)
      - Dopis 17: "Mírovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 225)
      - Dopis 18: "Mému nakladateli", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 226)
      - Dopis 19: "Karlíckovi - sochari", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 227)
      - Dopis 20: "Dvema Václavum", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 228)
      - Dopis 21: "Rudovi", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 229)
      - Dopis 22: "Docentu K.", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 230)
      - Dopis 23: "Olince", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 231)
      - Dopis 24: "Goldimu", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 232)
      - Dopis 25: "Anicce", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 233)
      - Dopis 26: "Panu porybnému", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 234)
      - Dopis 27: "Profesoru M.", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 235)
      - Dopis 28: "Nepochopené z Horního Ujezdu", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 236)
      - Dopis 29: "Na rozloucenou", [1947?] (Box 8, Folder 237)
      - Contracts, 1947-48 (Box 8, Folder 238)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 239)
    - "Západoindicky deník"
      - Contracts, 1928, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 240)
      - Correspondence about German and Dutch translations, 1930-35 (Box 8, Folder 241)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 242)
      - Publicity, 1928-29 (Box 8, Folder 243)
      - Reviews, 1929-30 (Box 8, Folder 244)
  - SHORT STORIES
    - "A.D.L.F."
      - Typescript: in Czech, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 245)
      - Typescript: English translation, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - "Balada o dokonalosti"
      - Typescript: Chapter II from "Stín", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 247)
    - [Berbersky autobus]: printed in "Dvanáct poutí svetem"
      - Correspondence with publishers, author's fee, publicity, 1940-41 (Box 9, Folder 248)
    - "Bloudení v exilu"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 249)
    - "Cas kouzelník"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 250)
      - Illustrations: 8 pen and ink sketches by the artist (Box 9, Folder 251)
      - Afrikaans translation, TLS about author's fee, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 252)
      - "Time, the Magician": English translation: typescript, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 253)
    - "Ceská zlatokopka v Klondike"
      - Typescript, [1955] (Box 9, Folder 254)
    - "Co by srdcem dohodil"
      See: "Bloudení v exilu", Box 9, folder 249
    - "The Counterpoint of My Life"
      - Typescript: in Czech, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - "A DP - Christmas Gift"
      - Typescript: in Czech, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 256)
      - Typescript: English translation, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 257)
    - "Dva Janové"
      - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 258)
    - "Filatelista"
      - Typescript: chapter IV from "Stín", n.d (Box 9, Folder 259)
    - "Le grand secret": printed in Lectures d'aujourd'hui: newspaper clipping, 1956 Feb 18 (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - "Is it the Same Town?"
      - Typescript: English translation of "Je to stejné mesto?", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 261)
    - "Je to stejné mesto?"
      - Typescript, n.d (Box 9, Folder 262)
    - "Kátinka"
      - Reviews, n.d (Box 9, Folder 263)
    - "Konec beze slov"
      - Typescript: chapter VI from "Na pocátku bylo slovo", n.d (Box 9, Folder 264)
    - "Legenda o sose svaté Emilie"
      - Typescripts, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 265)
    - "Legionárské novely"
      - Contracts, 1920, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 266)
    - "Manhattan"
      - First and second drafts, [1956?] (Box 9, Folder 267)
      - Printed in Sklizen, year IV, no. 4, one issue and newspaper clipping, 1956 Apr (Box 9, Folder 268)
    - "Milostny kruh; 9 príbehu o lásce"
      See: "Xenia", Box 10, folder 294
    - "Neprátelství"
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 269)
    - [No Man's Land?]
      - Typescript in English, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 270)
    - "Pojistka"
      - Typescript: chapter V from "Stín", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 271)
    - [Sága rodiny Emanuela Nemecka]
      - Draft corrected, incomplete, [1954?] (Box 9, Folder 272)
      - Research notes, [1954?] (Box 9, Folder 273)
    - "Der Schiffscoiffeur": printed in Sonntagsblatt der Solothurner Zeitung: German translation of "O lodním kaderníkovi"
      - Newspaper clipping, 1958 Nov 16 (Box 9, Folder 274)
    - "Smích"
      - Typescript and photocopy (Box 9, Folder 275)
      - Printed in Tribuna, year IX: newspaper clipping, 1957 Jun-Jul (Box 9, Folder 276)
    - "Stín"
      - Typescript: chapter I from "Stín", n.d. (Box 9, Folder 277)
    - "The Strange Case of the Postcard Collector": English translation of "Podivny prípad sberatele pohlednic"
      - Typescript and carbon, corrected (Box 9, Folder 278)
      - Typescript: unidentified draft, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 279)
      - Rejections, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 280)
    - "Svetlo vecné"
      - Typescript: chapter III from "Stín", n.d (Box 9, Folder 281)
      - "Tania Grekova": English translation: mimeographs, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 282)
    - [Tajemství Spojenych národu]
      - Typescript and corrected fragment (Box 10, Folder 283)
      - Printed in Hlas exilu, year V, no. 10: newspaper clipping, 1956 Oct (Box 10, Folder 284)
      - "Halfeen's nachts op Manhattan": Dutch translation printed in De Linie, no. 684: newspaper clipping, 1961 Nov 10 (Box 10, Folder 285)
      - "Secret of the United Nations": English translation: typescript and photocopy (Box 10, Folder 286)
      - "United Nations: to Practice Tolerance": English translation: unidentified draft, fragment, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 287)
    - "V polední pause"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 288)
    - "Vejír z poledníku"
      - Contracts, 1936-47 (Box 10, Folder 289)
      - Correspondence with publishers, 1936-37 (Box 10, Folder 290)
      - Reviews, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 291)
    - "Vltava se vlévá do Kaspického more"
      - Typescript, n.d (Box 10, Folder 292)
      - "The Moldau Flows into the Caspian Sea": English translation: typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 293)
    - "Xenia": 5th story of "Milostny kruh"
      - Author's fee, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 294)
      - Contracts and correspondence, 1941, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 295)
      - Reviews, [1975?] (Box 10, Folder 296)
      - French translation: typescript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 297)
      - German translation printed in Züricher Woche, nos. 34-38: newspaper clipping, 1958 Aug-Sep (Box 10, Folder 298)
      - German translation printed in Sonntagsblatt der Solothurner Zeitung, no. 45: newspaper clipping, 1958 Nov 9 (Box 10, Folder 299)
      - German translation printed in Roman fürs Heim, vol. 87: one issue, [1961?] (Box 10, Folder 300)
      - Related material: galley proofs of first 16 pages, proofs of illustrations, dust jacket, and reviews, [1941, 1946?] (Box 10, Folder 301)
    - "Zápisky z Velké Války, 1914-15"
      - Typescript, [1967?] (Box 10, Folder 302)
  - POETRY
    - "Az jednou v zimní podvecer": typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 303)
    - "Byl by to zázrak"
      See: "Pred svatym Vítem", Box 11, folder 341
    - "Bylina 54": typescript and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 304)
    - "Cas je nekdy bárin": typescript and photocopy, 1955 Jan 22 (Box 11, Folder 305)
    - "Cekalo devce": typescripts, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 306)
    - "Ceská modlitba": printed in Novy Domov: newspaper clipping, 1950 Sep 7 (Box 11, Folder 307)
    - "Churavé reky": holograph, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 308)
    - "Clovek a motyl": holograph and typescript, 1956 Sep 12 (Box 11, Folder 309)
    - "Dr. Dajan": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 310)
    - "Fierlingerovská castuska": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 311)
    - "Frána Tichy": typescript and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 312)
    - "Gratulace k svatbe Marjánky Winnové": typescript, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 313)
    - "Ilja Bolsán - Strachov"; "Pan Presny": typescripts, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 314)
    - "In memoriam Prokopa Tomáse Herbena": printed, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 315)
    - "Indocínská. L.E. No. 5"; "Urední hlásení"; "Zamil. komsomolec": holograph (Box 11, Folder 316)
    - "Jak most ten presli": typescript and photocopies, 1954 Mar 27 (Box 11, Folder 317)
    - "Jozka Kalvoda": typescripts and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 318)
    - "Kdybyste znali tu mansardu": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 319)
    - "Kdyz prisel jsi na svet, synu muj": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 320)
    - "Koleda," "Prostonárodní": typescript, [1954] (Box 11, Folder 321)
    - "Konecná stanice je dál": typescript, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 322)
    - "Láska na mape sveta": holograph, 1944 Jan (Box 11, Folder 323)
    - "Leica-li lije": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 324)
    - "Letenská balada": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 325)
    - "Mé divadlo": printed in N[ew Yorské] l[isty?]: newspaper clippings, [1955 Jan 15] (Box 11, Folder 326)
    - "Muze se, bratre, stát": typescripts, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 327)
    - "Nehledejte...": typescript and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 328)
    - "Noc na Lysé Hore": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 329)
    - "Ohnivá zeme": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 330)
    - "Pan doktor Hajda": holograph (Box 11, Folder 331)
    - "Pan Kalvoda": typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 332)
    - "Pan Presny": typescripts, photocopy, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 333)
    - "Pan Satan": holographs and typescript (Box 11, Folder 334)
    - "Pan Tichy": typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 335)
    - "Písnicka": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 336)
    - "Písnicka realisty": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 337)
    - "Pochod vojensky": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 338)
    - "Popravenym": typescript and newspaper clippings, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 339)
    - "Pozdrav": typescripts, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 340)
    - [Pred svatym Vítem]: holograph, signed, and typescript, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 341)
    - "Proc jsem setrny a nikoly marnotratny (Vlastní epitaf)": printed in an unknown source: clippings - photocopies, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 342)
    - "Prosba": printed in [ Sklizen ], year III, no. 7: newspaper clipping and photocopy, 1955 Jul (Box 11, Folder 343)
    - "Réva si zpívá": typescript, corrected and signed, and carbon (Box 11, Folder 344)
    - "Rozbijes retezy": typescript, p. 1 wanting, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 345)
    - "Sedmnáctileté": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 346)
    - "Selská modlitba": typescript, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 347)
    - "Signál": first and second drafts, typescripts (Box 11, Folder 348)
    - "Soumrak": typescripts, 1956 Aug 21 (Box 11, Folder 349)
    - "Svázíme urodu (Podle Vladimíra Majakovského)": typescript, [1950?] (Box 11, Folder 350)
    - "Tiché hrdinství": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 351)
    - "Tomásovo Never - more!": typescript, carbon, signed, 1943 Oct 4 (Box 11, Folder 352)
    - "Truchlohra": printed in Lidové noviny, year 47, no. 285: newspaper clipping and typescripts, 1939 June 9 (Box 11, Folder 353)
    - "Ukolébavka"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 354)
      - Holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 355)
    - "United Field Theory": typescripts and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 356)
    - "Vánocní poselství 1952": printed in [ Svoboda ]: newspaper clipping (Box 11, Folder 357)
    - "Verím v Boha, stvoritele more i zeme, také té zeme, kterou jsem musel opusit": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 358)
    - "Verná láska": holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 359)
    - "Víra": typescript, [1955?] (Box 11, Folder 360)
    - "Vylet amerického pana Broucka na ceské brambory": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 361)
    - "Vylet s. Broucka do prítomnosti": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 362)
    - "Závet'"; "Elegické distychon mé záveti": typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 363)
    - "Zdenek Nesmírny": first and second drafts, typescript (Box 11, Folder 364)
    - "Zpev o srdci nasí chvíle": printed in Sklizen, year III, no. 2: newspaper clipping and typescripts, 1955 Feb, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 365)
    - "Zrada zivlu": holographs and typescript (Box 11, Folder 366)
    - "Zvon svobody": typescript, carbon, and photocopy (Box 11, Folder 367)
    - "Pepe: Frantisku, mám k tobe dotazy": holograph, fragment, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 368)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - Articles
      - "Canadas problemer": printed in Politiken, in Danish: newspaper clipping, 1950 Aug 2 (Box 12, Folder 369)
      - "Co by se mohlo..."
        - Typescript, [1957?] (Box 12, Folder 370)
        - Printed in Ceské slovo, year 3, no.3: newspaper clipping, 1957 Mar (Box 12, Folder 370)
      - "Ctvrty cervenec a jeho tvurcové": written for RFE and printed post- humously in Denní hlasatel: newspaper clippings (2), 1958 Jul 1,2 (Box 12, Folder 371)
      - "Dopis redatorovi": typescript, [1955] (Box 12, Folder 372)
      - "Jak jsem se setkal s ctenári své knihy": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 373)
      - "Jan Löwenbach - 75.narozeniny"
        - Typescript, [1955?] (Box 12, Folder 374)
        - Printed in New Yorské listy, vol. LXXX, no. 51: newspaper clipping, 1955 Apr 28 (Box 12, Folder 374)
      - "Jeník v Novém svete": printed post- humously in Novy domov, vol. VIII, no. 52: newspaper clipping, 1957 Dec 28 (Box 12, Folder 375)
      - "Jindriskova farma": printed in [ New yorské listy ]: newspaper clipping, 1959 Jul 18 (Box 12, Folder 376)
      - "Legionári, první vojsko rupubliky": typescript (2 copies), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 377)
      - "Meditace legionárská"
        - Typescripts (2 copies), [1957?] (Box 12, Folder 378)
        - Printed in Ceskoslovenské noviny, year III, no.5: newspaper clipping and the whole issue, 1957 May (Box 12, Folder 378)
      - "Meditace politická"
        - Holograph and draft A, typescript, [1959?] (Box 12, Folder 379)
        - Draft B, typescript, [1959?] (Box 12, Folder 380)
        - Printed in Ceské slovo, year 5, no.1 (2 issues): newspaper clippings, 1959 Feb (Box 12, Folder 380)
      - "Mezi Huterány a podivíny": printed in Nase hlasy, vol. IV, no.17: newspaper clipping, 1958 Aug 9 (Box 12, Folder 381)
      - "Mír 1953 - zlaté slovo": typescript and photocopy (Box 12, Folder 382)
      - "Nedali jsme lidstvu...": printed in Hlas domova, year VII, no.10: newspaper clipping and photocopy, 1957 May 13 (Box 12, Folder 383)
      - "Paul Brock, Esq.": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 384)
      - "Pohádka o starém dome v Michalské ulici": printed posthumously in Novy Svet: newpaper clipping and photocopy, 1957 Dec 24 (Box 12, Folder 385)
      - "Prohlásení Rady...o úmrtí Klementa Gottwalda"
        - Typescript, [1953] (Box 12, Folder 386)
        - Printed in Denní hlasatel: newspaper clipping and photocopy, 1953 Mar 17 (Box 12, Folder 386)
      - "Prsten": printed in New yorské listy: newspaper clipping and photocopy, [1953?] Apr 4 (Box 12, Folder 387)
      - "Rudé námluvy u 'Svobodné Evropy'": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 388)
      - "Le secret des Nations Unies"
        See: Oversize, Box 29, folder 920a
      - "Slovo o spisovatelích"
        - Typescript and photocopy, [1954?] (Box 12, Folder 389)
        - Printed in [ Nase cesta ] no.5: newspaper clipping and photocopy, 1954 Sep (Box 12, Folder 390)
      - "Svetlo v chaosu..": printed in Amerika Masarykovi: 1 issue and photocopy, 1955 May (Box 12, Folder 391)
      - "Tanger": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 392)
      - "V záplave svetel": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 393)
      - "Verse exulantu": printed in Ceskoslovensky prehled, year 1, no.8: photocopy, 1954 Oct (Box 12, Folder 394)
      - "Vzpomínka na Jozku Filipa historického jara 1945: a memoir": typescript, [late 1940's] (Box 12, Folder 395)
      - "Vzpomínka na rodny kout": typescript, [1940?] (Box 12, Folder 396)
    - Interviews and Reviews
      - Ett.: "Kobenhavns ansigt har aendret sig": in Danish, printed in Politiken, year 73, no. 271: newspaper clipping and photocopy, 1957 July 2 (Box 12, Folder 397)
      - "Jan M. Kolár: Listy nemému príteli" (Box 12, Folder 398)
        - Typescript, [1956?]
        - Printed in Sklizen, year IV, no.2, 1956 Feb
        - Also P. Ruzicka's: "K Nemeckove recensi 'Listu nemému príteli": printed in Sklizen, year IV, no.6, 1956 Jun
      - "K clánku 'Oc prosí ceská skola ceské umelce'": typescripts, [1946?] (Box 12, Folder 399)
      - Printed, edited version in Pedagogicky pruvodce: newspaper clipping, 1946 Dec 2 (Box 12, Folder 399)
      - "Koptove hre na uvítanou": printed on the program of J. Kopta's play Blázen Kabrnos: clipping and photocopy (Box 12, Folder 400)
      - "'Palicova dcera': kritika Tylovy Palicovy dcery, [1954?] (Box 12, Folder 401)
      - "Posudek Z. Nemecka o románu Vladimíra Dudinceva 'Nejenom chlebem'": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 402)
    - Speeches
      - "28. ríjen 1918 a dnesek": typescripts. Includes invitation, 1956 Oct 27 (Box 12, Folder 403)
      - "I am speaking on behalf of a country": typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 404)
      - "Kdo byl vynen únorovym prevratem": mimeographs, 1952 Mar 19 (Box 12, Folder 405)